I had talked several
times now about valid or
invalid constellations
in class diagrams.
In particular, remembering last
week, we had said that
in the context of inheritance, it is
not allowed that there is, say, cyclic inheritance.
Or a class
inheriting from itself.
Or a class being duplicate subclasses
of another class, so to speak.
However, I had also emphasized in
this week's videos that there are
no such restrictions for association
and then also for aggregation.
We had
also seen examples.
An example of such a
constellation, and also a cyclic one.
Yes, a cycle of association
and aggregation relationship would be okay.
It looks
different for composition.
So:
For association/aggregation,
no restriction
on cycles/self-reference or presence of
multiple relationships between same classes.
For composition, however, cycles of
any kind are again forbidden.
So for composition there
must be no such cycle.
With composition there
must be no self-reference.
And there must not be any two
classes which are directly cyclic in this form.
Here, in fact, the direction
of the containing relation is important.
So this is forbidden here because one
could contain oneself here in the circle.
And also here the problem
is that there is this cycle,
because the two
compositions are directed opposite.
If one would turn this relationship around here and
"E" would contain "F" in two ways, so to
speak, then this could still be valid
depending on the multiplicities that are on it.
We'll discuss that on a
slide in a moment as well.
The important
thing here is:
These are really prohibitions
that are specific to composition.
So, if you were
to replace one of the
compositions here with an aggregation,
it would be legal again.
So the aggregation and
also association don't count with
respect to this
restriction for composition.
There it's really about the fact that you're
not allowed to draw circles with composition, for example.
Now what
about non-cyclic relationships?
For example,
double composition
relationship between two partners, but
not in this cyclic way?
Even then, there are still
limitations, and they come from the
fact that yes, a part may not belong
to more than one whole at the same time.
And that this is something
that goes beyond multiplicities alone.
So, for example,
in these relations there
are situations which simply do
not make sense with the multiplicities.
You would be allowed to syntactically write
"1" to each of these two ends here.
But one could then never
generate an object diagram for it.
One could not specify any objects "a", "b",
"c" of the classes "A", "B", "C", which would
fulfill this in
any meaningful way.
Because each object of the class C would have to
belong, if here a 1 and here a 1 would stand,
always at the same time to an object of the
class A and to an object of the class B.
But that is forbidden, because a part
may not belong to more than one whole
at the same time
when it comes to composition.
And in
a similar way
restrictions arise even
beyond the syntactic requirement.
One cannot have multiplicity
1 at both compositions.
Because then one could
not form meaningful instances.
One would have to look at
that more exactly, what is permitted here.
Which constellation is
allowed here or not.
I will probably do
that in an extra video.
It should also
be noted that
association/aggregation/composition also
interacts with inheritance.
This is because a subclass always inherits
associations, aggregations and compositions from the superclass
in addition to
attributes and methods.
For example, if we have a class
diagram in the following form, yes we
have a composition between A and C, an aggregation
between B and C, and B inherits from A.
Then B inherits from
A also this composition.
That is, there is obviously an
aggregation between B and C here, but
there is also a
composition due to the inheritance.
And that in turn
holds potential for conflict.
If this were a composition,
then it would not look
like there are
any duplicate compositions.
But since B inherits from A, there would
then suddenly be two compositions between B and C.
This is not the case now,
because we have composition and aggregation.
But in general,
inheritance also ensures
that association/aggregation/composition
is inherited.
And then that can have consequences, for instance,
for this question of the presence of composition cycles.
So that's what has
to be paid attention to.
Here, things don't get
in each other's way now.